HariPrakash VelMurugan

602-860-2993 | hvelmuru@asu.edu | linkedin.com/in/hari-prakash-v | https://github.com/hariprakash619

SUMMARY

Software Engineer with experience in backend development, microservices, and full-stack engineering. Led impactful projects at PwC, optimizing data-intensive operations, modernizing legacy applications, and reducing processing times through efficient code restructuring and microservices transitions. Open to both New Grad and mid-level roles in backend development, full-stack engineering, and infrastructure.

EDUCATION

Master of Science in Computer Science

December 2024

Arizona State University

CGPA 3.93/4.0

Coursework: Data Mining, Distributed Database Systems, Machine Learning, Algorithms, Data Structures, Cloud Computing.

B.Tech. Computer Science and Engineering

May 2018

Vellore Institute of Technology

Coursework: Computer Architecture, Database Systems, Theory of Computation, Operating Systems, Applied Linear Algebra.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming: Python, JavaScript, C, C++, Bash, SAP ABAP, SAP Fiori, HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, Typescript. Database: SQL, MySQL, PostgreSQL, NoSQL, MongoDB, ElasticSearch, SAP HANA DB, DynamoDB.

Frameworks & Others: Flask, React, Node.js, Redis, GitHub Actions, Linux.

Git, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS(S3, RDS, IAM, SES), Kafka, Android, Prometheus, Grafana, Postman. **Technologies:** Postman API Fundamentals Student Expert | Meta Back-End Developer Professional Certificate. **Certifications:**

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Price Waterhouse Coopers Senior Software Engineer

India

April 2022 - December 2022

- Directed backend optimization initiatives, shifting data-intensive operations to database layer, which achieved a 40% reduction in SQL query processing time and boosting system reliability.
- Implemented **REST APIs** to transition to microservice architecture, reduced system-wide failures by isolating faults to individual services.
- Revamped legacy application through strategic refactoring, bug fixing, and upgrades, significantly bolstering maintainability.
- · Managed team of 2, trained and guided on agile, version control, increasing code quality and maintainable codebases.

Price Waterhouse Coopers

India

Software Engineer

September 2018 - March 2022

- Developed Planning and Production Lifecycle Application deploying MVC design pattern, cutting manual processing time by 80%, errors by 90%, accomplished adoption by 50 teams, streamlining operations.
- Architected 12+ custom dashboards leveraging Javascript libraries, driving data-driven decisions and boosting revenue by ~15%.
- Designed Travel Management Application to automate approval process, cut down approval time by 20%, errors by 33% and boosted user satisfaction with revised efficiency and usability.
- Upgraded data entry process by integrating barcode solution using javascript libraries, improved accuracy by 25%, and reduced errors.
- Modularized over 10,000+ lines of code to build reusable components, reducing development time by 30%.

Invento Robotics

Software Engineer Intern

January 2018 - July 2018

- Created image recognition API leveraging Python and integrated into Flask web app, improving scalability and reducing response time.
- Worked with product managers to define and deliver new Android Application, resulting in a 40% increase in user engagement.
- Led efforts in troubleshooting, testing, and optimizing software, minimizing deployment errors through CI/CD pipelines and Docker.
- Executed an image recognition feature by storing images in AWS S3, utilizing EC2 for processing and RDS for database management.

PROJECTS

Non-Profit STEAMSuperheors Opportunity Hack 2024

Utilized Flask, Python, AWS Lambda, S3, DynamoDB, IAM, and SES to run features such as mentor mentee matching, scheduling, secure admin access with OTP-based authentication, and email notifications for non-profit which helps underprivileged students.

Real-Time Notification System

Designed and developed a real-time notification system, converting static APIs into dynamic, event-driven services on Kafka. Attained reduction in latency and restructured system's responsiveness for high-volume traffic. Tools: Python, Confluent Kafka, ksqlDB.

NetFlex Content Delivery Network

Built a high-performance CDN with advanced caching and sharding strategies. Leveraged Docker Compose to orchestrate MongoDB server images, ensuring resilient and scalable deployment. Tools: PostgreSQL, Docker, Compose.

Computer Vision API with PyTorch and MLOps

Deployed Flask app with a vision model powered by TensorFlow, incorporating MLOps best practices for streamlined deployment.

AWARDS

- Placed Second at Opportunity Hack 2024 conducted by Meta | Second Place in Code-A-thon conducted by Hacker Devil @ ASU.
- Awarded "Team Spot Award", "Spot Award" for exceptional contributions at PwC.